Guide to the Victor Serge Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1912-1947; Series II; 4.8; (12 boxes)
  - ARTICLES
    - [Socialism], drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, [1942?] (Box 5, Folder 276-278)
      "4. Matérialisme historique"
      "5. La fonction de l'intelligence"
      "6. Marxisme et psychologie"
      "7. La question religieuse"
      "9. La deuxième internationale"
      "10. Le mouvement syndical"
      "15. La IVe internationale"
      "16. La révolution espagnole"
      "Psychologie du nationalsocialisme"
      "Definition des Sozialismus"
      "Der Sozialismus - eine Wissenschaft?"
      "Psychologie und Marxismus"
      "Die religiöse Frage"
      "Die Gewerkschaften"
      "Psychologie des Nationalsozialismus"
      "Sozialismus und Psychologie"
      See also: Box 14, folder 582
    - "Socialisme et psychologie," typescript, corrected, 1947 Mar (Box 5, Folder 279)
      "Socialismo y psicología,"
      typescript carbon
    - "Socialisme et questions coloniales," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Nov (Box 5, Folder 280)
    - "Le souvenir de Vladimir Illitch," drafts, typescript (fragment) and carbon, photostat (Box 5, Folder 281)
      See also: Box 12, folder 443
    - "Souvenirs sur le Komintern," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 May (Box 5, Folder 282)
    - [Soviet Union after World War II], typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 283)
    - "La succession de Franco: déclarations d'Indalecio Prieto," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Nov 12 (Box 5, Folder 284)
    - "Sur le conflit russo-polonais et le régime de l'URSS," draft, typescript, corrected, and holograph carbon, 1944 Aug (Box 5, Folder 285)
    - "Sur le problème basque," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 286)
    - "Sur les routes du Caucase," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Aug (Box 5, Folder 287)
    - [Telegrams?], typescript carbon, 1921, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 288)
    - "Le temps de la destruction," typescript, corrected, 1945 Apr 10 (Box 5, Folder 289)
    - "Le temps de la terreur et de l'enthousiasme," outline, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 290)
    - "Le temps du courage intellectuel," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Jan (Box 5, Folder 291)
    - "Thèses sur la révolution russe," typescript carbon, corrected, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 292)
    - [Totalitarianism, Marxism, and capitalism], drafts, typescript and carbon (3 copies) (Box 5, Folder 293)
    - "Tour d'horizon," typescript, 1937 Jan 2 (Box 5, Folder 294)
    - "Tout recommence," typescript carbon, corrected, 1936 Dec 29 (Box 5, Folder 295)
    - "Trente ans après la révolution russe," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1947 Jul-Aug (Box 5, Folder 296)
    - [ La tribuna israelita ], typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 297)
    - "Le troisième printemps de cette guerre mondiale...," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Apr 6 (Box 5, Folder 298)
    - [Trotsky and his Leur Morale et la nôtre ], typescript carbon, corrected (Box 5, Folder 299)
    - "Le trotskysme," typescript carbon, 1942-43 (Box 5, Folder 300)
    - "Vers la formation d'un gouvernement espagnol en exil," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Aug 11 (Box 5, Folder 301)
    - "Vers un nouveau tournant de la guerre mondiale," typescript carbon, corrected (3 copies), 1942 Aug 20 (Box 5, Folder 302)
    - "Vers un renouvellement du socialisme?," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Jan (Box 5, Folder 303)
    - "Vieux carnets," typescript carbon, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 304)
    - "Vladimir Korolenko"
      See: Box 21, folder 662
    - "Vladivostok, clé de l'extrême- orient," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 305)
    - [Letter to the editor of La voie de Lénine ], typescript carbon, corrected, 1939 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 306)
  - BOOKS
    - L'affaire Toulaév
      - Plan for a novel, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 307)
      - Outline and notes (Box 6, Folder 308)
      - Title page and table of contents, typescript carbon, corrected (Box 6, Folder 309)
      - Early chapter drafts, holograph, typescript, and carbon, corrected (Box 6, Folder 310-313)
      - Early chapter drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 6, Folder 314-316)
      - Intermediate drafts, Ch. I-II (2 copies), typescript and carbon (Box 6, Folder 317)
      - Later chapter drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 6, Folder 318-320)
      - "Note of the author", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 321)
    - L'an I de la révolution russe
      See also: Box 21, folder 650
      - Notes, typescript, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 322)
      - Preface, draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1938 Sep (Box 7, Folder 323)
      - Page proofs, corrected, of title pages, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 324)
    - Les années sans pardon
      - Outline and notes, 1946 Nov 8 (Box 7, Folder 325)
      - Early chapter drafts, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 326-329)
      - Early drafts of untitled chapters, holograph, typescript, and carbon, corrected (Box 7, Folder 330-331)
      - Intermediate chapter drafts, typescript, corrected, 1946 Nov 8-14 (Box 7, Folder 332-333)
        Annotated: "Commencé le 4
        septembre 1945 à Mexico"
      - Later chapter drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 334-335)
        Annotated: "Commencé le 5 sept. 45
        à Mexico"
    - De Lénine à Staline
      - Front cover of published version, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 336)
      - Signed (by VS) page of published version, n.d.
      - Clipping of review, n.d.
      - Excerpt from unidentified work that possibly cites De Lénine à Staline, n.d.
    - Les derniers temps
      - Outline, draft, holograph, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 337)
      - Early draft, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 8, Folder 338-342)
      - Later chapter drafts, typescript, corrected, 1945 Jun 10 (Box 8, Folder 343-346)
        Begun 1943
      - Advertisements, 1945-47 (Box 8, Folder 347)
      - Lists of people to whom books were sent, 1946 Oct 1 (Box 8, Folder 348)
      - Clippings of reviews, 1946, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 349)
    - [ Destin d'une révolution ], typescript carbon, corrected (Box 8, Folder 350)
    - Hitler contra Staline
      See also: Box 3, folder 163
      - Advertisements, 1942, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 351)
      - Clippings of reviews, 1941, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 352)
    - Les hommes dans la prison, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 353)
    - Mémoires d'un révolutionnaire
      See also: Box 21, folder 653
      - Chapter outlines, drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 354)
      - Notes, holograph, typescript, and carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 355)
      - Chapter drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 9, Folder 356)
      - "I. Monde sans évasion possible... (1906-1912)," drafts, typescript carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 357-358)
      - "I. La défaite," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 359)
      - "II. Encore la défaite...," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 360)
      - "III. Le tournant obscur...," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d.
      - "IV. Essénine," drafts, typescript and carbon (2 copies), corrected (Box 9, Folder 361)
      - "V. L'opposition de Léningrad," typescript and carbon, corrected
      - "VI. L'agitation et la plateforme," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 362)
      - "VII. Le schisme de novembre 1927," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected
      - "VIII. Premières persécutions," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 363)
      - "IX. Le drame de la collectivisation," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 364-365)
        Also titled "La collectivisation
        de l'agriculture"; "Débuts de la
        collectivisation"
      - "X." [Untitled], typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 366)
      - "XI. La défaite d'Allemagne (1923)," drafts typescript and carbon (3 copies), corrected
      - "XII. Vienne, porte des Balkans... (1925)," drafts, typescript and carbon (3 copies), corrected (Box 9, Folder 367)
      - Chapters XIII-XIV (untitled), drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 368)
      - "Expérience personnelle," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 369)
      - "Pleine attente (notes sur un voyage de Paris à Mexico)," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d.
    - Naissance de notre force
      - German translation, clippings of serial version, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 370)
      - Clippings of reviews, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 371)
    - Le nouvel impérialisme russe
      - Clippings of advertisement and review, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 372)
    - Portrait de Staline
      - Plan and outline for update and expansion of earlier book, holograph and typescript carbon, 1946 Dec 8 (Box 10, Folder 373)
      - Clippings of reviews, 1940-43, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 374)
      - Fan mail, 1940, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 375)
    - S'il est minuit dans le siècle
      - Chapter drafts, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 376-380)
      - [Plan of Orenburg made by Vlady at the request of Victor Serge, which serves to situate the novel S'il est minuit dans le siècle ], holograph, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 381)
      - Clippings of reviews, 1939-46, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 382)
      - Fan mail, 1939-40, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 383)
    - La terre commençait à trembler
      See: L'affaire Toulaév, Box 6, folder 307
    - Le tropique et le nord
      - Table of contents, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 384)
      - Clipping of review, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 385)
    - Vie de Staline, translation of Stalin by Leon Trotsky
      - Partial draft, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 10, Folder 386-388)
        Pages 1-223.
      - Fragment of draft, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 389)
        Pages 102-27 (two copies), 128-39,
        and 139-63.
    - Vie et mort de Trotsky
      See also: Box 16, folders 617-622
      - Binder with inscribed title, holograph, in unidentified hand (Box 11, Folder 390)
      - Notes, holograph and typescript (Box 11, Folder 391-396)
      - Table of contents (3 copies), typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 397)
      - Fragment of unidentified chapter, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 11, Folder 398)
      - Early draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 399)
      - Later chapter drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 Jun (Box 11, Folder 400-403)
      - "Notes complémentaires," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 404)
  - CONFERENCES
    - [Centro Cultural Ibero-Mexicano], speaking notes, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 405)
    - "Europa en 1941"
      - Speaking notes, drafts, typescript and carbon, 1941 Nov 13 (Box 12, Folder 406)
      - Invitations and clippings, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 407)
    - "La poésie russe depuis 1917," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 408)
  - NEWSPAPER AND JOURNAL CLIPPINGS
    - Acción social
      - "El asesinato de los líderes socialistas polacos Herlich y Alter", 1943 May 15 (Box 12, Folder 409)
      - "Los communistas mexicanos forman un nuevo frente", 1947
      - "El congreso de Londres y el porvenir de la internacional sindical", 1945 Feb 15
      - "¿Durara el stalinismo?", 1945 Mar 15
      - "Polonia y el porvenir de Europa", 1944 Dec 15
    - La batalla (Barcelona)
      - "Contra la calumnia", 1937 Jan 7 (Box 12, Folder 410)
      - "En legitima defensa", 1937 Mar 3
      - "El fin de Yagoda", 1937 Apr 15
      - "El recuerdo de Vladimir Illitch", 1937 Mar 7 (Box 12, Folder 411)
      - "Sobre un poder fuerte", 1937 Jan 6
      - "Todo se repite", 1937 Jan 3
      - "En torno a un crimen", 1936 Sep 27
    - Bohemia (Havana)
      - "La segunda fase de la invasion", 1942 Aug 16 (Box 12, Folder 412)
    - The Call (New York)
      - "The Russian People Have Earned the Right to Full Democracy", 1946 May 20 (Box 12, Folder 413)
      - "The War and the Resurgence of Socialism--An Optimistic Approach", 1943 May 7
      - "Will Stalinism Last?", 1945 May 14
    - Claridad
      - "De Victor Serge à sus amigos", 1937 (Box 12, Folder 414)
    - El combatiente rojo (Madrid)
      - "Contra la calumnia", 1937 Jan 13 (Box 12, Folder 415)
      - "Todo se repite", 1937 Jan 8
    - L'école émancipée
      - "Une lettre de Victor Serge", 1947 May 11 (Box 12, Folder 416)
    - L'émancipation paysanne
      - "Staline contre les paysans", 1940 Feb 3 (Box 12, Folder 417)
    - La flèche
      - "Moeurs florentines", 1936 Nov (Box 12, Folder 418)
    - Masses
      - Announcement of article by Serge, 1946 Dec (Box 12, Folder 419)
    - Mundo
      - "Sobre la revolucion hindu", 1943 Jul 2 (Box 12, Folder 420)
      - "U. R. S. S. pueblo y regimen", 1943 Jul
    - La nacion
      - "Hitler contra Stalin: el III Reich, agonizante", 1941 Jul 11 (Box 12, Folder 421)
    - The New International (New York)
      - "Again, Riazanov and Sneevliet", 1942 Sep (Box 12, Folder 422)
        Addressed to Max Shachtman
    - The New Leader (New York)
      See also: Box 1, folder 61
      - "The Death of Oumanski", 1945 Feb 10 (Box 12, Folder 423)
      - "Diego Rivera Succumbs", 1946 Jun 15
      - "Free Germany in Mexico", 1945 Jan 20
      - "Free Spanish Gov't Gains Wide Support, Represents Majority", 1943 Dec 18
      - "In Defense of André Gide", 1944 Dec 2
      - "'Jacson' -- Privileged Assassin", 1947 Apr 5
      - "Negrin Loses Ground in Spanish Maneuvers", 1945 Aug 25 (Box 12, Folder 424)
      - "A Plebiscite for Spain: The Problem of the Liquidation of Franco", 1945 Dec 22
      - "Popular Front in Latin America", 1943 Jul 17
      - "Stalin's Drang nach Osten: Mongolia as a Russian Base of Operations in Asia", 1945 Aug 18
      - "Stirrings in Spain", 1945
      - "The Trotsky Murder - GPU Fails to Save Jacson from 20-Year Term", 1943 May 8 (Box 12, Folder 425)
      - "Ukrainian Writers in the DP Camps", 1947 Apr 26
      - "Unity - Communist Style", 1945 May 26
      - "Who Will Succeed Franco? An Interview with Indalecio Prieto", 1944 Dec 16
      - "Writers Held in Bondage", 1947 Jan 4
      - Announcements of articles by Serge, 1945, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 426)
    - P. O. U. M. (Madrid)
      - "Una carta de Victor Serge dirigida à La batalla ", 1936 Oct 14 (Box 12, Folder 427)
    - La révolution prolétarienne
      - "Les écrits et les faits", 1937 Sep 25 (Box 12, Folder 428)
    - Rumbo
      - "Balance de la reacción staliniana", 1941 Oct-Nov (Box 12, Folder 429)
    - Tierra y libertad
      See: Box 21, folder 661
    - Todo
      - "'Todo' siempre esta abierto a la discusion serena", 1943 May 20 (Box 12, Folder 430)
        See also: Box 2, folder 79
    - La Wallonie
      - "Le 14 juillet 1789", 1938 Jul 16-17 (Box 12, Folder 431)
      - "Adieu à Gramsci", 1937 May 8-9
      - "Adieu à un ami", 1937 Aug 14-15
      - "L'amer", 1936 Jun 27-28
      - "Angel pestagna", 1937 Dec 18-19
      - "Angoisse et confiance", 1938 Oct 1-2
      - "L'anniversaire du 18 mars", 1937 Mar 20-21
      - "Appel à la raison", 1936 Nov 14-15
      - "Après la défaite...", Apr 30
      - "Au dernier congrès des soviets", 1936 Dec 12-13
      - "Au seuil de la campagne d'hiver", 1936 Oct 24-25
      - "Autriche, grand cimetière de l'Europe", 1938 Jun 28
      - "Baltika", 1939 Jul 1-2 (Box 12, Folder 432)
      - "La bataille de Guadalaraja", 1937 Oct 30-31
      - "La bête humaine", 1936 Sep 12-13
      - "Bezymenski", 1937 Aug 21-22
      - "Le Birobidjan, république juive", 1938 Jul 9-10
      - "Blucher", 1938 Aug 20-21
      - "Boris Pilniak", 1937 Jul 31
      - "Boukharine", 1937 Nov 27-28
      - "Le bourrage de crâne", 1937 Jul 24-25
      - "Carlo Rosseli", 1937 Jun 19-20 (Box 12, Folder 433)
      - "Ce qui naît...", 1936 Sep 19-20
      - "Choses d'Espagne", 1937 Mar 27-28
      - "Christianisme et propriété", 1937 Jan 16-17
      - "Le commencement...", 1938 Mar 26-27
      - "Complots en U. R. S. S.?", 1938 Mar 19-20
      - "Crime et criminologie", 1938 May 8
      - "La crise de l'industrie soviétique", 1937 Sep 25-26
      - "La crise de l'U. R. S. S.: l'affaire Kossarev", 1938 Dec 3-4
      - "De Ejov à Béria", 1938 Dec 17-18 (Box 12, Folder 434)
      - "De la guerre civile à l'économie dirigée", 1936 Dec 8
      - "Défaite de la Chine", 1938 Oct 31
      - "Défense de la culture...", 1938 Jul 30-31
      - "Défense du pilote", 1936 Oct 10-11
      - "Destin de l'occident", 1936 Apr 10
      - "Deux conceptions de l'histoire", 1939 Feb 11-12
      - "Deux héros", n.d.
      - "Disparition à Moscou...", 1939 Jan 21
      - "La disparition du Maréchal Blucher", 1938 Oct 22-23
      - "Dix-huit congrès...", 1939 Mar 18-19
      - "Données sur l'Espagne", 1936 Aug 21
      - "Le drame de Krestinski", 1938 Apr 3
      - "Le drame des juifs d'Allemagne", 1938 Nov 20
      - "Le drame russe", 1939 Jan 30-31
      - "Edouard Berth", 1939 Jan 9 (Box 12, Folder 435)
      - "Un empire des steppes...", Jun 11
      - "En soixante-sept ans...", 1938 Mar 29
      - "Équilibre instable...", 1939 Mar 25-26
      - "Espagne, creuset politique", 1939 Feb 19
      - "L'esprit européen", 1936 Aug 8-9
      - "L'évolution du droit pénal en U. R. S. S.", 1937 Jul 16
      - "Fascisme et mensonge", 1937 Apr 3-4 (Box 12, Folder 436)
      - "Fièvres en Tunisie", 1937 Jan 5-6
      - "Le film et l'histoire", 1936 Sep 26-27
      - "La fin de la révolution française", 1939 Aug 20
      - "La fin d'une épopée", 1937 May 29-30
      - "La fin d'une grande actrice", 1939 Jul 30
      - "Les flèches noires à Bilbao", 1937 Aug 28-29
      - "Francesco Ghezzi", 1938 Jan 15
      - "Gide, retour d'U. R. S. S.", 1936 Nov 22 (Box 12, Folder 437)
      - "Grandes dates de novembre", 1938 Nov 5-6
      - "La guerre de Chine", 1937 Oct 2-3
      - "La guerre du mensonge", 1937 Jul
      - "Hitler 1923", 1938 Oct 15-16
      - "Il y a vingt ans...", 1937 Mar 6-7
      - "Il y a vingt ans", n.d.
      - "Imminence de la guerre?", [1938] Feb 19-20
      - "L'indéfendable"
      - "Juifs de Russie...", 1939 Apr 8-9 (Box 12, Folder 438)
      - "Les juifs et la révolution", Jun 24
      - "Juin 36", 1938 Jun 11-12
      - "Langage de raison", Apr 16
      - "Lumières sur l'U. R. S. S.", 1939 Apr 1-2
      - "Marx et Bakounine", 1939 Aug 13 (Box 12, Folder 439)
      - "Mécanisme des catastrophes", 1938 Jun 5
      - "Message à Charles Plisnier", 1937 Dec 11-12
      - "Le Mexique à l'honneur...", 1938 Apr 10
      - "Mineurs des Asturies", 1936 Oct 17-18
      - "Mort de Rosa Luxembourg", 1939 Jan 14
      - "Mort d'un ami...", 1937 Feb 26-27
      - "Musée du soir...", n.d.
      - "Le mystère des aveux", n.d.
      - "Une négociation laborieuse", Jun 17 (Box 12, Folder 440)
      - "Ni paix ni guerre?", 1938 Sep 17
      - "Noël 1936", 1936 Dec 25
      - "Noire année 1938", 1938 Dec 31
      - "Nouveau moyen âge", 1938 May 1
      - "Une nouvelle législation du travail", 1939 Jan 7-8
      - "Nouvelles de Moscou...", 1938 Jun 17-18
      - "Un numéro des Izvestia, 1939 Nov 26-27
      - "Le passé de l'Espagne", 1936 Jul 25-26 (Box 12, Folder 441)
      - "Pensée dirigée", 1937 Aug 24-25
      - "Pensons à Barcelone!", 1939 Jan 29
      - "Le plus triste voyage d'André Gide", 1936 Dec 19-20
      - "Plutôt Luddendorf...", 1938 Jun
      - "Le poète de la commune", n.d.
      - "Pour une cause sacrée", 1937 Feb 6-7
      - "Production et démocratie", 1937 Jul 17-18
      - "Les protocoles des sages de Sion", 1938 Dec 10-11
      - "Qu'est-ce que la culture?", 1937 Sep 18-19 (Box 12, Folder 442)
      - "Raskolnikov", 1939 Aug 5-6
      - "Remarques sur la révolution française", 1939 Jul 23
      - "Remarques sur l'antisémitisme", n.d.
      - "Le renvoi de Litvinov", 1939 May 13-14
      - "Les rescapés", 1938 Dec 24-25
      - "Retour à la puissance", 1936 Jun 20-21
      - "Retour à l'occident", 1936 Jun 12-13
      - "Révolutions et tyrannies", 1938 Jul 23-24
      - "Rome à la fin du XVe siècle", 1939 Jul 16
      - "Le sang des meilleurs...", 1936 Oct 4-5 (Box 12, Folder 443)
      - "Le sens de l'histoire", n.d.
      - "Signes d'affolement", 1938 Feb 12-13
      - "Le souvenir de Vladimir Illitch", 1937 Jan 23-24
      - "Souvenirs", 1936 Jul 8
      - "Stalinisme et libre-examen", n.d.
      - "Sur le drame espagnol...", 1939 Mar 11-12
      - "Tchang-kai-shek", 1938 Sep 3-4 (Box 12, Folder 444)
      - "Technique du mensonge", 1939 Feb 25
      - "Le témoignage d'Alexandre Barmine", 1939 Mar 4-5
      - "Le temps présent...", 1936 Nov 28-29
      - "Le temps présent...", 1939 Jun 3-4
      - "Une ténébreuse affaire", 1939 May 20-21
      - "Terre des hommes", 1939 Mar 27-28
      - "Terreur blanche en Espagne", Apr 23
      - "La thèse chinoise", 1938 Aug 27-28
      - "La thèse japonaise", 1936 Aug 13-14
      - "Tour d'horizon", 1937 Jan 2-3
      - "Tour d'horizon", 1938 Oct 8-9
      - "La Victoire de l'Espagne républicaine est-elle possible?", 1937 Sep 4-5 (Box 12, Folder 445)
      - "Villain, l'assassin de Jaurès, s'était engagé dans les bandes de Franco", 1937 Jun 16
      - "Visages de la terre", 1938 Mar 5-6
      - "Yagoda", 1937 Apr 10-11
    - Unidentified
      - "De Zaak Kossarew", 1938 Dec 16 (Box 12, Folder 446)
      - "Democracia o totalitarisme", 1947 Aug
  - NOTES
    - "1936" [day book], holograph, in notebook, 1936 Apr-Oct (Box 12, Folder 447)
    - "Fin 1936" [day book], holograph, in notebook, 1936 Oct-Dec (Box 12, Folder 448)
    - "Agents staliniens," holograph, typescript, and carbon (Box 12, Folder 449)
    - [ Analysis, no. spécial, Titre: La guerre et la démocratie socialiste...], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 450)
    - [Applications à l'observation historique], holograph, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 451)
    - [Auden, W. H. For the Time Being ], holograph, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 452)
    - "Biologie de la connaissance-?," holograph, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 453)
    - "Carnets, 1937-1938 (Bruxelles, Paris)," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 454)
    - [Character developments?], holograph, typescript, and carbon (Box 12, Folder 455)
    - "Cieza de Léon, cronica del Peru (1547), publiée à Séville 1553," typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 456)
    - "Codé," holograph, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 457)
    - "Demain: néo-fascisme ou socialisme?," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 458)
    - [Dmitrovna, Tat'iana. Orenburg?], holograph, in notebook, 1935-36 (Box 12, Folder 459)
      In envelope labeled [Samye laskovye
      stranitsy V. S.]
    - "Discusion sobre la función de las democracias en esta guerra," typescript and holograph, corrected, 1942 Apr (Box 12, Folder 460)
    - "Écrivains français," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 461)
    - [Fonction des guerres et des guerres civiles...], holograph (Box 13, Folder 462)
    - [Jews in Mexico], typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 463)
    - [Jouhandeau, Marcel. L'amateur d'imprudences ], holograph (Box 13, Folder 464)
    - [Lambert, George], typescript, 1937 Jan 27 (Box 13, Folder 465)
    - "La liberté," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 466)
    - [Marx: le synthèse...], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 467)
    - "Matériaux pour un roman de moeurs sur Leningrad," holograph, corrected (Box 13, Folder 468)
    - "Message à pleine voix...," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 469)
    - [Mexican politics], typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 470)
    - [Mexico], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 471)
    - [Mexique. Notes], holograph, typescript, and carbon (Box 13, Folder 472)
    - [Meyer, Conrad Ferdinand. Verses], holograph (Box 13, Folder 473)
    - [Mouvement ouvrier], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 474)
    - [Nazism], typescript carbon (2 copies), 1944 Sep (Box 13, Folder 475)
    - "Necessity of Free Information and Discussion for the European Trade- Union and Socialist Movements," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Jun 2 (Box 13, Folder 476)